There's a fascinating new study that
shows that our health is not only
affected by our nutrition, our exercise,
our genetics, and all the other aspects
of health that we've come to know, but
also the time of day, specifically
nighttime. And no, I'm not talking about
sleep. I'm talking about eating later in
the day being potentially more harmful
to our health. Now, why is that? Well, a
great simple illustration of that is
insulin resistance. the condition that
is fundamental to type 2 diabetes.
Essentially, if the cells of your body
are unable to uptake glucose molecules
floating in your bloodstream and you're
highly likely to be insulin resistant,
as glucose levels rise, your pancreas
secretes the antidote insulin to bind
the insulin receptors of your cells,
which triggers a cascade inside the
cells to allow doorways called glucose
transporters to populate the cells
membranes, thereby allowing glucose from
the blood into the cells, reducing blood
glucose. If any part of that is
inhibited, that's called insulin
resistance. So keep that in mind. Now
let me show you a simple illustration in
data. The red is people who are
generally in poor health. So poor liver
health, overweight, etc. And the blue is
people who are in better health. So
we're measuring the amount of glucose
that is taken up by the cells of the
body per unit of insulin. So, the higher
the bars, the better the insulin
sensitivity. Or, well, said differently,
the lower the bars, the more insulin
resistant. But we're looking at two
different times. One measure during the
day and another measure at night. And
that's where the problem lies. While
yes, predictably in day measures the
control, the healthier group has better
insulin sensitivity than the unhealthy
group, the real gem is the comparison
between day and night measures in the
unhealthy group. Notice how at night
their insulin resistance worsens. This
is not the case for those who are
healthier. So this tells us that people
who are generally less healthy,
especially with metabolic dysfunction,
have even worse insulin resistance later
in the day into night. The questions
that come to mind are A, why is that?
And B, what can we do to prevent this
nighttime insulin resistance? Now, one
reason comes down to something called
gluconneogenesis.
That's a fancy term to describe the
creation of new glucose molecules, the
very same found in the bloodstream that
we're trying to control through insulin.
This gluconneogenesis process occurs in
the liver primarily. And when we test it
in people, there's a higher proportion
of glucose being produced by the liver
and being released into the bloodstream,
keeping glucose levels higher than
normal in an insulin resistant state.
That's especially telling because
insulin also binds our liver and reduces
our gluconneioenesis.
But here, well, we're seeing the process
does not happen so readily. Ultimately,
we are not clearing glucose because
insulin resistance and we are also
raising blood glucose with an inability
to stop new glucose production. All of
this happening especially at night.
Okay, so less sensitivity to insulin at
night, more glucose being spilled out of
the liver at night due to lack of
sensitivity to insulin. Good stuff.
Well, not really, but you get the point.
But what if we're blaming insulin
resistance unfairly? I say that because
of data like this, which is incredibly
illuminating as to why these things
happen at night. We're measuring
pancreas insulin secretion rate. So, we
want those lines to stay nice and
steady. But, do they all look nice and
steady? I think I'll take no for 500.
Look at the metabolically compromised
insulin secretion at night. It dips way
down. So, not only are people
potentially insulin resistant, they're
also simply secretreting less insulin.
Fascinatingly, this does not happen
during the day. What I can tell you is
that your body also clears insulin. So
if it produces it, it has to clear it
too. And fascinatingly, there's a
slightly faster clearance of insulin in
those that are metabolically
compromised. So to paint a whole picture
here, people who are in poor health, as
in more body fat, more insulin
resistant, metabolic profile is poor,
have greater difficulty clearing
glucose. They produce more glucose in
the liver, produce insulin at a slower
rate, and even clear insulin more
quickly at night. This is a big deal
because it's a lot of different
physiological issues all because of the
time of day. But I'm not here to just
bring bad news to you. I'm not Gandalf
Stormcrow. So, knowing all that, what do
we do? I'm going to get into some of the
things to do that this paper describes
and how persistent of an issue this can
be. But I actually have two more studies
that I'm going to go over on timing
exercise, as well as some additional
fascinating mechanisms on the cross talk
between fat cells and the liver and even
some issues with mitochondria. If you're
interested, I cover all that in the
extended edition of the video that
you're watching right this very moment.
It's included with my Physionic Insider
membership, including a full article,
one paragraph takeaways, live sessions
with me, and so much more like all these
perks right here. If you're inclined to
check it out, use the link in the
description. I would love to have you
aboard. One obvious solution to these
problems would be to well uh I don't
know uh lose weight, specifically lose
body fat. Now, in addition, I should
mention that all the data that we went
over earlier is what's known as
cross-sectional. So, we're simply
matching two groups of people by age and
sex and look at some other
characteristics and comparing them,
hoping the only major difference in
their metab is their metabolic health.
However, this isn't a controlled way to
do research. So when we actually have
people undergo weight loss through
improved nutrition for 12 weeks, we see
that we see that that their body fat
normalizes, their liver enzymes
normalize and more even to the point
that they become similar to the
healthier controls that we were just
comparing against earlier. So the
question is then does weight loss
through better nutrition lead to a
reversal of all these nighttime problems
within the body? The answer is
not really. One example is shown here.
We're looking at insulin secretion.
Again, all the lines correspond to the
people with metabolic dysfunction, but
the purple lines are after 12 weeks of
weight and fat loss. Now, fascinatingly,
there's still a significant reduction in
insulin secretion at night. So, this
could imply permanent damage. Now, I'm
not so bold enough to claim that yet,
but even with significant other
improvements like in liver health and
total body fat, the problems that we
discussed earlier, at least some of
them, they do seem to persist. So then,
what do you do? Well, we can turn to
another study that tested the timing of
nutrition when all else is equal and the
impact that it has on insulin
resistance. We see the results here.
were measuring insulin resistance and
the lower the bars, the better. Clearly,
one group did much better than the
other. So, what did they do? They simply
pushed all their meals to the beginning
and the middle of the day. That's it.
Now, I voiced my concerns about
nutrition studies looking at
intermittent fasting like this because
we can't control for the fact that the
control group ate their last meal much
later the previous day. So the
differences in insulin resistance might
be explained by the fact that the
intermittent fasting group just hadn't
eaten for a longer period of time. This
is a real limitation to these kinds of
studies. Still, there is a real result
here, reduced insulin resistance. In
fact, other measures also improve like
the pancreas being more responsive,
meaning releasing more insulin. Do I
think this is a end all beall evidence?
I do not. But it's moderately strong
evidence that simply changing the timing
of your food consumption may help combat
the issues that we discussed that happen
at night for metabolically compromised
individuals. I'd also remind that while
this habit may be beneficial for people
who are generally healthy, the results
that we went over at nighttime insulin
resistance, reduced insulin secretion
and greater insulin clearance and all
that shebang that we were exclusively in
people with long-term metabolic
dysfunction. So, if you're healthy, your
blood values are generally in the normal
ranges. You do not need to change
anything. Plus, keep in mind that while
this study was extensive, it still
included only a small group group of
people. And even with the weight loss,
the participants with nighttime
metabolic dysfunction still weighed more
than the control group, even if their
total body fat percentage was the same.
Now, I'm pointing this out because it
leaves room for the possibility that the
other differences could explain the
maintained issues in spite of the weight
loss. All this to say, this is a cool
study and it tells us a lot, but more
studies need to be done to confirm this
in a more robust way. Anyway, I hope
this was informative as always and
there's more on insulin resistance right
here. I'll catch you in that very next
one. I'll see you over there. Thank you
for tuning in. See you.